Late September 1941,
Operation Barbarasa has been underway
for 3 months.
Tens of millions of Soviets are under
Nazi rule.
They've seen their towns bombed, their
farms and villages looted and destroyed.
Hundreds of thousands of Jews, men, as
well as women and children have been
slaughtered.
Some 2 million Red Army soldiers have
been killed or captured.
The Soviet Union is on its last legs
in Kev. Arena Karachinova cannot accept
the German occupation.
>> We are living in the horror brought on
by the ocean of blood unleashed every
hour, every minute by idiots in gray
green coats whose belts are inscribed
with the words, "God is with us."
At first, we thought we were going to
die to stop breathing.
It isn't true.
People are resilient. They can endure
anything.
Since early September, the Vermachar has
advanced on every front.
Kev is conquered. Leningrad under siege.
Smolins, a barrier on the road to Moscow
has fallen.
For Hitler, it's vital to take advantage
of this momentum to launch a major
offensive against the capital before
winter. Operation Typhoon will be the
decisive battle which will bring the
campaign to an end.
Henrik Harper, the army doctor, is
gearing up for the attack.
Since June, half the young men in his
battalion have died.
The only thing that matters to him now
is saving those who are left.
I order the troops to not eat 6 hours
before the start of the offensive.
This way, the soldiers will have a
better chance of survival in the event
of a whim to the stomach.
I warned them that eating just one slice
of bread increases blood flow to the
intestines and that in the event of
injury, this will cause more severe
internal bleeding.
The troops launching the offensive have
been severely weakened by the heavy
fighting over the summer. But the
prospect of getting the operation over
with boosts their morale and the
soldiers throw everything they have into
the attack.
October the start of Operation Typhoon,
heavy fire rains down on the Soviet
forces.
The panzas rapidly pierce the defense
lines of the Red Army, which is still
mired in leadership problems and
incapable of coordinating its efforts.
On October the 3rd, a Panza division
takes Oral on the road to Moscow after a
lightning advance of over 200 km.
As unlikely as it sounds, the tank
operators encounter Soviet workers who
wave to them, believing they are
compatriots.
Fed by Stalin's propaganda, the
population is unaware of the Germans
swift advance.
With the Panza's help, German infantry
and artillery units managed to encircle
the Soviets yet again.
October the 6th, just 4 days into
Operation Typhoon, a first cauldron
closes around Soviet forces at Brians.
On October the 7th, a second encircled
Soviet troops at Viasma.
Almost 100,000 dead on the Soviet side,
substantial losses on the German side in
men and equipment.
Helmuch, a Vermar lieutenant colonel,
flies low over the battlefield. a
committed anti-Nazi. He secretly
disapproves of this war.
Bodies of Russians piled on top of each
other everywhere.
Artillery positions pulverized along
with their guns and gunners by our
pancers.
Wagons destroyed.
Horses wandering about with their
saddles under their bellies.
Vehicles in flames.
Burnt out villages.
It is like a kaleidoscope of horrifying
impressions passing before my eyes
which I cannot forget.
Hope of a forthcoming end to the war is
unrealistic. As long as part of this
world is subjected to the criminal will
and the deranged ambitions of a madman.
The Germans themselves are surprised by
the size of their hall.
25,000 officers, including a dozen
generals, are captured.
650,000
prisoners in all soldiers,
nurses,
as well as peasants who found themselves
trapped in the encirclements.
Marupople falls on October the 14th,
Odessa on the 17th, Karkov on the 24th.
The rice press chief exclaims on the
radio, "The Soviet Union is liquidated."
Hansrot on the front in Ukraine is not
fooled by this propaganda.
We hear on the radio, "The end of the
war in the east is near."
That put my head in my hands. Have our
leaders gone mad?
For the love of God, the reality is
altogether different. If only people
knew what was really going on here.
Our mothers, our wives will be overjoyed
to hear that this terrible bloodshed is
finally coming to an end. And they will
expect their men to be home by
Christmas.
Back home, the awakening will be harsh.
The newspapers will be covered in black
crosses like never before.
At the same moment in Moscow
after the catastrophic defeat at Viasma
and Brians, the anti-aircraft defenses
cannot stop the German planes.
Every night they drop hundreds of
explosive and incendurary bombs.
Civilian volunteers spend their nights
on the city's rooftops looking out for
projectiles.
With their scant resources, they try to
prevent fires.
The authorities may well claim the
situation is under control. The
population is starting to think the city
will fall.
Giorgi Efron finds himself totally alone
at 16.
He has seen his mother fall apart and
commit suicide. He has lost every point
of reference.
Practically everyone here is convinced
of the imminent and decisive defeat of
our army. And yet Moscow is living in
cloud cuckoo land.
On the one hand, the papers speak of
military trophies, the Red Army's heroic
resistance, and say Moscow will always
be Soviet.
On the other, everyone returning from
the front, and they are many. Talk about
the sorry state of the Red Army and
catastrophic defeats.
Some people maintain that the Germans
will enter Moscow tonight.
That's an exaggeration,
but anything is possible.
>> Danger looms. Archives are burned.
Government buildings mined.
Civil government officers and their
cohorts of public servants are evacuated
900 km to the east.
Has Stalin planned to leave?
He alone knows.
But according to his Ed Deon, his boots
have been packed just in case.
On the morning of October the 16th, the
first workers are astonished to find the
underground stations closed.
Even the familiar propaganda voices are
silent.
The city's loudspeakers only play
vianese waltzers.
The rumor immediately spreads. The city
has been abandoned by the authorities.
Stalin has fled. It's time to leave.
Those who managed to reach the railway
station are turned away. There is only
room on the trains for party members.
On the edge of the city, feeling
betrayed, Muscovites stop the cars of
the privileged elite as they attempt to
flee.
One of them recounts,
"A mob was blocking the road."
All of a sudden, some men jumped on our
car. Others banged on the roof and the
bonnet.
They smashed all of the windows. Then,
dozens of hands lifted up the car and
flipped it on its side.
My wife was literally dragged from her
seat.
>> The soldiers there to keep order were
powerless.
The political militia turned a blind
eye.
Just as I was about to be lynched,
someone recognized me and said I was the
author of a famous book about the Civil
War. That saved my life.
In Lenengrad, the 2 and a2 million
residents are cut off from the rest of
the country.
A month and a half prior, the Germans
decided to lay siege to the city. An
attack would have been needlessly costly
in terms of men.
Leningrad, the birthplace of the Bolevik
revolution, would have defended itself
house by house.
But the siege will wear down the
inhabitants and the city will fall.
Leuba Chaparina is a theater designer, a
leading figure on the art scene.
Since the war started, she's worked as a
nurse to support herself and her son.
She notes in her diary,
"Last night, there was an air raid
warning at the hospital. The bombing was
so intense that we assembled all the
wounded in the corridor, where the roar
of the explosions is pretty much
muffled."
We read the newspaper out loud to them.
I began my evening duties. put drops in
eyes, applied compresses.
Then I reluctantly returned to the
bandage room.
Inside, I really had the impression the
bombs were extremely close and that my
time was coming.
German artillery bombards the city
around the clock.
food warehouses, apartment buildings,
fuel depots, hospitals.
Dozens are killed every day.
Liuba Chaparina is revolted.
I cannot understand.
My mind refuses to accept the senseless
barbarity of the Germans who even
bombard the hospitals.
Blast bombs and incendry devices have
been dropped. There are countless
casualties.
Many people have been burned.
Why are they doing this? To show they
respect no one. We already know that
future generations will but be appalled
by this unspeakable savagery.
Hitler personally ordered the blockade.
We will not enter Russian cities. They
must be destroyed completely. We need
not have any qualms. We're not
nursemaids. We have no obligations to
these people. There's only one task to
set about the Germanization of the land
by bringing in Germans and to regard the
indigenous inhabitants as Indians.
Lieutenant Colonel Helm Steif plans
operations with the high command behind
the front lines.
He's dismayed by the manner in which his
superior officers are conducting the
war.
Their geometry on maps, as he writes to
his wife, is completely detached from
the reality of the battlefield.
Since Operation Typhoon began, our
divisions have lost more men than in the
early days of the offensive.
But for all that, this has not led to
any sort of realization.
The demands grow ever more excessive.
They will lead to self-destruction
and filled with the deepest hatred.
The goal of operation typhoon was the
capture of Moscow before winter.
But as the veh progresses deeper into
Russian territory, the supply situation
becomes critical and Soviet resistance
increasingly fierce.
The German command's grand plans found
her in the mud of the Rasbutita, which
in the autumn turns dirt roads into
swamps.
The troops find themselves literally
stuck in the mud in the open countryside
200 km from Moscow.
General Hinriki is stuck with his men.
In his diary, he writes,
>> "At best, it takes a truck 36 hours to
cover 35 km.
Fuel, bread, oats, nothing is getting
through.
The horsedrawn wagons are stuck. the
cannons, too. All of the men, infantry,
and others are pushing more than they're
fighting.
Everywhere there are cries of, "I can't
take it anymore.
Private Villi Peter Resza is on the
front line.
In his notebook, the young writer
expresses his rage and helplessness.
Murky streams run over the roads. The
ground is soden.
With each step, our boots sink deep.
Covered in clay, scarred with crusted
mud. We advance through the filth and
our drenched gray coats and boots.
Everything is wet. Bread, clothing.
There's no refuge.
In these extreme conditions,
what will become of the Soviet prisoners
who now number over 3 million?
Regarded as subhumans, underfed,
deprived of medical care, the Germans
have never been concerned about their
fate.
With the war dragging on and severe
logistics issues, their plight worsens.
They are forced to trudge great
distances behind the front lines only to
be confined in makeshift open air camps.
They're reduced to eating dirt, bark,
grass, rodents,
and their belts.
Ena Corova has a step-brother imprisoned
in a camp near Keev. She knew the
prisoners were starving, but did not
expect such cruelty.
They look so dreadful that a shiver of
horror runs through me.
They're not fed, that's for sure.
Women rush over to the prisoners. They
throw the morsels of food to stave off
their hunger.
The men pounce like wild animals on the
scraps they managed to catch.
The Germans beat the men's heads with
the butts of their rifles.
They hit the women, too.
But the women carry on regardless.
I feel I'm witnessing
under a beautiful autumn sky a scene of
hell straight out of the Middle Ages.
In the month of October 1941 alone, some
5,000 Soviet prisoners of war die every
day.
powerless to help them. The population
is especially affected by their fate.
They are mujiks, their brothers, their
husbands, their children.
Early November, for General Guy Zhukov,
who's directing the defense of Moscow,
the mud of the Rasbutita is a stroke of
luck. He thinks the Germans will be
unable to resume their attack for at
least two weeks.
Chosen by Stalin for his iron grip, he
makes the most of this reprieve to
remotivate civilians and soldiers alike
by resorting to strong armed tactics.
Order number 345. 1. All cowards who
leave their positions be shot on the
spot.
Two, the military tribunals must ensure
this order is carried out to the letter.
Comrades of the Red Army, not one step
back.
Moscow is transformed into a fortress.
Barricades and obstacles of all sorts
are erected all over the capital.
Hundreds of thousands of civilians,
women for the most part, are conscripted
to dig anti-tank ditches around the
city.
Giorgi Efron, the young orphan, is
evacuated from Moscow after being
shunted from one home to another.
I have to leave everything again.
So long, beloved comfort. blankets,
table and bedroom, my dear Moscow.
Back to railway stations, the unknown
and difficult living conditions.
Despite all, I still believe in a bright
future, or at least moments of
happiness.
The privilege of youth,
maybe.
I admit it helps me to keep going.
This war will end eventually.
on November the 7th. It snows on Moscow.
The Germans are 80 km from Red Square,
but Stalin insists on presiding over the
traditional military parade
commemorating the Bolevik Revolution.
It is the opportunity for him to
galvanize the people with another great
patriotic speech.
who vanquished the Tutonic Knights.
Kutusov who defeated Napoleon.
Stalin cites the great legendary figures
who symbolize the resistance, the
grandeur and the invincibility of
eternal Russia. He exhorts his army and
its young recruits to live up to their
glorious ancestors.
[cheering]
One of the Soviet Union's great
strengths is its virtually inexhaustible
manpower reserves.
In November, hundreds of thousands of
reserveists are mobilized.
Over 1 million 18 and 19year-olds are
called up.
The Red Army was virtually wiped out in
Minsk, Crane, Viasma, and Brians.
But it is rising from the ashes.
At the same moment in Leningrad,
the Germans genocidal objective becomes
clearer by the day.
They've cut off the last supply routes
to the city.
They've laid minefields to decimate the
starving, attempting to flee,
dying of starvation or freezing to
death.
That is the fate that awaits the
inhabitants.
They spend their days looking for wood
to keep warm, wandering in the cold in
search of subsistence.
They take water from broken water manes.
Food is rationed.
A high school student writes in his
diary,
"I was unable to buy the 400 g of
cereal, the 615 g of butter, and the 100
g of flour for the next 10 days.
These products are nowhere to be found,
and where there is food, the lines are
huge.
Hundreds upon hundreds of people in the
street, in the cold, and there is only
enough for a handful of us.
Freezing, people cue and go home
empty-handed.
A young woman confides.
>> Why hunger?
Because the Germans were quick to
realize
it is what most undermines the spirit of
resistance.
Hunger is a permanent state that cannot
be halted.
It is always present. You feel it
constantly.
What is most dreadful is seeing your
rations disappear and not feeling full.
With no food to be had, ration coupons
have become useless.
The city is littered with corpses.
Everyone ignores them.
Leuba Japarina sees her and her son's
deaths approaching. She can no longer
bear the indecency of the propaganda.
On all the pictures, Stalin's
unbelievable smuggness is apparent.
How is he now? The stupid bastard who
truly believed he was the greatest, the
almighty, the wisest, the emperor, God.
My heart is broken.
For the 23 years of bulcheism, it was as
if we were all on death row.
But now we really are.
We have reached the end.
The end of our age.
An in glorious end.
By the end of November 1941,
11,000 residents of Lennengrad have died
of starvation
and 52,000 more at the end of December.
By the time the siege ends two years
later, 800,000 will be dead.
At the same moment, 1,000 km south of
Leningrad,
stopped by the mud, the German soldiers
occupy villages and towns.
For 3 weeks now, General Hinriki has
been stuck. He writes to his wife.
For now, we are living in a wretched
village.
Our shacks are crawling with bugs.
Many men have fallen ill because of the
appalling weather.
Our boots are worn out. Our clothes
falling to shreds.
My men keep asking me when will this all
be over.
All I can do is shrug my shoulders and
saying, "I don't know.
On November the 13th, the general staff
and army commanders meet for a special
conference in [music] Orcher behind the
central front. The issue is crucial. The
cold has frozen the mud. Operation
Barbarasa could resume.
Most of the commanders are against
continuing the offensive. Aware both
troops and equipment are depleted and
the supply lines overstretched, they
prefer to sit out the winter. But
General Halder, the mastermind behind
Barbarosa, refuses to stop so close to
the goal. The troops must give
everything they possibly can.
The German will shall triumph.
It's become a
full marsh of the roll band.
And so on November the 15th, the Germans
resume the offensive.
The troops surge forward for a time,
advancing a few dozen kilometers,
but soon come up against a wall.
The Soviets fierce defense of their
capital.
As a result, this new offensive does not
strike a decisive blow or achieve a
breakthrough.
Ground is one bit by bit in a slow and
bloody advance.
The infantry division of Army Dr.
Hinrich Harper advances furthest,
reaching a tram terminus on the
outskirts of Moscow.
We stopped, fascinated by the wooden
seats on which thousands of passengers
had sat and waited for the tram into
Moscow.
There was an old wooden waste paper
basket attached to the wall. I searched
it and pulled out a handful of used tram
tickets.
Characters in cerillic we knew spelled
the name Moscow.
Moscow, city that had haunted our
thoughts during our long march,
which now seemed to loom before us like
a mirage.
Hinrich Harper's battalion never made
the last few kilometers to the capital.
Two weeks later, instead of achieving a
rapid breakthrough as the general staff
had hoped, the German armed forces
ground to a halt once more.
In this ultimate offensive, they
expended their remaining strength.
80 cases of fainting due to exhaustion
are noted in a company of fuseliers.
In the 23rd division, although the
closest to Moscow, two battalions refuse
to advance.
According to their commanding officer,
>> the losses in men and officers are
simply too heavy, and we've run out of
munitions. We feel incapable of
advancing another kilometer.
The Russians resistance has become too
strong.
We never thought the Russians would
defend their capital with such
determination.
They kept fighting until we stopped.
In enemy territory with few
possibilities of finding shelter, the
cold becomes a major problem.
Most soldiers have not received their
winter uniforms.
They wrap themselves with newspaper,
wear straw over boots, and layer upon
layer of clothes, sometimes taken from
the enemy's corpses.
In his diary, Vilipa Razer gives a raw
account of their degeneration.
Do we need boots? We take them from old
people and women on the roadside.
We do not want to. We have no choice.
Our
cooks slaughter calves and pigs found
along the way.
But it is not enough. So we pinch
women's and children's last morsels of
bread. We stuff into our knapsacks the
little butter and fat they have left.
Load our vehicles with lard and flour
taken from their reserves. Drink their
milk. Steal honey.
Their tears, their pleas, their curses.
Do not bother us.
He sees himself become a stranger to
himself.
We suffer from diarrhea.
Our stomachs are fermenting bogs. We
disgust ourselves.
My life and my mind can no longer ignore
the fatigue, the desire to flee, the
need for sleep, hunger.
The torture of the forced marchers has
made us so bitter that we have become
insensitive to the suffering of others.
We show off our illgotten gains and
delight in the impression we make with
our pistols on a defenseless woman who
is unlucky enough to be Russian.
There are two things which can unite
men. Common ideals and common
criminality, boasted Hitler.
Operation Barbarasa is a war of
annihilation that has never spared
[music] civilians.
But in late November, the exactions
against the population reach new
heights.
Faced with a possibility of defeat,
afraid the people will take revenge,
[music] the German soldiers see the
enemy everywhere.
Isolated deserters, partisans,
Jews.
The vermarked run a mock in a frenzy of
violence.
Not only do they hang individuals
suspected of partisan activities, but
hundreds of villages are destroyed and
their inhabitants murdered as part of a
policy of preventative punishment.
Early
December in Kev. The city has been
occupied for two and a half months.
Ena Corova does not know exactly what's
going on at the front, but she senses
the wars at a turning point.
One only has to read between the lines
to realize that the Germans are not
leaping from victory to victory as they
claim.
In fact, they are not advancing on any
front.
Lenenrad is resisting and Moscow has not
fallen.
I know, and I'm not the only one, that
our army is preparing for battle and
fully mobilizing their reserves of men
and equipment.
We live in hope of seeing the moment
when the Nazi hordes will be driven back
and return whence they came.
December the 6th in Moscow, General
Zhukov decides to take advantage of the
Vermachar state of exhaustion to launch
a major counter offensive.
The Germans are taken by complete
surprise.
They thought the Russian forces were
exhausted, worn out. They discovered
that the Red Army has managed to
mobilize new forces.
Wave after wave of Soviet infantrymen
hurl themselves into the attack.
Godard Henriki and his men find
themselves cornered in a small town near
Moscow.
December 16th. I am writing in a state
of extreme anxiety.
The Russians have pierced our defense
line in a number of places and forced us
to retreat.
I don't know how this is going to end.
December 17th.
Everything would not be going so badly
if we had not worn out men and officers
in 6 months of non-stop combat, crushing
our bodies and souls.
December 20th,
we completely underestimated the
Russians.
December 24th,
calamity looms.
And up there in Berlin, no one sees it.
For Viper Raza, the situation is equally
desperate.
There is no one between his unit and the
Russians.
>> Silent, bitter, stupid, ghostlike. We
flee westwards like shadows.
We call for help over the radio, but
where we are, no one can help us.
[screaming]
Several men collapse. They refuse to get
up. They refuse to budge.
We kick them, pug them with our rifles.
miserable, their eyes empty. They get up
and start walking.
Anyone who stays behind is on his own.
He freezes
or the Russians find him and beat him to
death.
Zukov's counter offensive achieves its
objective of pushing the Germans back
from Moscow.
up to 130 km in some areas.
For Hitler, a route must be avoided at
all costs.
On December the 18th, he issues the
halter beail or halt order. The troops
must stay where they are, put up a
fierce fight. Any retreat is forbidden.
in the Red Army's front line. Nikolai
Nicolen finds himself in this face off
with no way out.
My mind was dull and barely alive in my
famished and weary body.
My soul only rarely stirred.
Whenever I had a free moment, I closed
my eyes in the darkness of the shelter
and remembered my home,
the summer sun, flowers, the Hermitage
Museum,
books I loved,
familiar melodies, and the faint flicker
of hope would warm me in that dark and
icy world of cruelty, starvation, and
death.
I forgot reality which merged with the
madness of my dreams.
Christmas 1941.
The German soldiers have not returned
home.
Operation Barbarasa has failed.
After 6 months of combat, the Vear and
the Red Army resemble two punch-drunk
boxers staying precariously on their
feet but rapidly losing their power to
hurt each other.
The vermar has not taken Lenengrad or
Moscow, but it is still standing.
The Red Army has not destroyed the Vmar,
but it has saved Moscow.
Both Stalin and Hitler refuse to give
up. They're counting on fresh reserves
and better equipment to deal the fatal
blow.
Since the German invasion began, the Red
Army has lost 5 million men. The
vermarked 800,000,
a quarter of its initial number.
But these huge numbers are just the
start of the hecatum of World War II.
By the end of the war, 4 million
soldiers will have perished on the
German side and 11 million soldiers and
16 million civilians on the Soviet side.
I have only rarely wept.
Weeping is pointless when you're in the
midst of events.
When we meet again and I can unburden
myself,
we will need to weep a lot
and you will be able to understand your
husband.
Here it is pointless.
Even before the most terrible scenes,
we're engulfed with despair and guilt.
Overwhelmed with shame. Sometimes I'm
even ashamed to have been loved.
This German infantryman was killed near
Kashira, 115 km south of Moscow in
December 1941.
The letter was found in his pocket.